时间索引：05:05 - 有什么相同，
06:00 - 有什么不同 // 发动机和燃料，
23:05 - 有什么不同 // 尺寸，运载能力，制造，花费，
32:15 - 有什么不同 // 一级火箭重复使用，
41:50 - 有什么不同 // 二级火箭重复使用，
53:40 - 总结
Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
嗨 我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
As most of you probably know
你们中的大多数人可能知道
we're witnessing the biggest, most powerful, most ambitious rocket ever built come to life before our eyes.
我们正在见证有史以来(体积)最大 (能力)最强大 (工程)最艰巨的火箭逐渐成真
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
视频来源：youtu.be/-8p2JDTd13k
原视频发布日期：20201106
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
校对：dbenyong，zerOxidi欧希
个别专有名词翻译出处：www.elonx.net/spacex-stories-how-did-spacex-rocket-engines-get-their-names
twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1291849720973783040
Yes, of course.
是的 当然
We're talking about SpaceX's Starship.
我们说的是SpaceX的Starship
This thing is the ultimate challenge in aerospace engineering.
这是航天工程的终极挑战
It's a fully and rapidly reusable, Super Heavy lift launch vehicle
它是一个可快速重复使用的超级重型运载火箭
capable of taking around 150 metric tons to lower earth orbit.
近地轨道运载能力大约150公吨
And yes, that is more payload than the Saturn V.
是的 这比土星五号的有效载荷还要多
And don't forget it does that while being fully reusable,
而且别忘了 它是在完全可重复使用的情况下完成的
but Starship's ultimate purpose goes way beyond just terrestrial orbital ambitions.
但Starship的最终目的 不仅仅是为了实现地球轨道上的目标
如果按照已制造并试飞实物的进度来计算的话……
Starship is the first vehicle really designed to actually take human beings to Mars and bring them back again.
而且它是第一枚真正设计用来载人登火并返回的航天器
In order to achieve this absolutely bonkers goal, SpaceX has had to employ a litany of new technologies.
为了实现这个绝对疯狂的目标 SpaceX不得不采用一连串的新技术
Use new materials, develop the most advanced rocket engines ever made
(比如)使用新的材料 开发有史以来最先进的火箭发动机
and come up with some really wild ideas that have never really been tried before
并提出了一些从未真正尝试过的疯狂想法
and perhaps for a good reason.
而且这么做的理由或许很充分
So today let's go over all of these new technologies
那么今天我们就来介绍一下这些新技术吧
and compare it to SpaceX's Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy to help point out what things are new,
并将其与SpaceX的猎鹰9号和重型猎鹰进行比较 有助于指出哪些东西是新的
what things are different and what they've learned from the Falcon family
这之中有什么不同 而他们从猎鹰家族那里学到的东西
that will apply to Starship in order to really understand just how ambitious this project is,
将应用于Starship 以便真正了解这个项目有多么地艰巨
but we're not just going to be scratching the surface here.
但我们不仅仅是停留在表面
Oh no. In fact, we're actually going to be taking you inside the rockets
不不不 实际上 我们会给你揭示这些火箭的内在部分
and showing you basically every single part and going over all the systems with a fine tooth comb
并基本上向你说明每个部件 并仔细梳理所有的系统
so that you can learn as much as possible.
以便让你能学到尽可能多的东西
So that means there's a ton to cover.
那么这就意味着有很多内容要讲
And because starships evolution is finally slowing down just a little bit,
而且因为Starship的演化终于慢了一点儿
this can be your definitive guide to Starship for now.
那么 这个视频可以给你作为目前Starship的权威指南了
Let's get started,
我们开始吧
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
and liftoff!
起飞
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
Now right off the top of here before we get started.
在我们开始之前 我想恰个饭
I just wanted to quick point out our awesome Future Martian Society T-shirt
that I'm wearing that has lots of awesome little nods to Starship.
You can find out more at everydayastronaut.com/shop. Okay.
Watching Starship come to life. Sure is addictive.
看着Starship逐渐成真 真是让人大呼过瘾
The general public has never had access to a rocket's development like this before.
公众从来没有像这样了解过一枚火箭的发展历程
I just love watching all the updates roll in from Elon Musk's Twitter,
我就是喜欢看马一龙的推特上的涌入的那些更新
but also from Mary and the NASASpaceflight crew SPadre, LabPadre, RGV Ariel, and Austin Barnard.
但也包括Mary和NSF论坛的成员SPadre，LabPadre，RGV Ariel和Austin Barnard
I mean every single day, there's some awesome content out there.
我是指每天都有些很好的内容出来
I don't really seem to recall a time
我好像真的不记得会有这种情况
when any company started building a product before they really had a factory.
那就是会有公司在真的建好工厂之前就开始制造产品
And then they just started building a factory around the product.
之后他们才开始围绕产品建厂
I guess Boca Chica is just kind of backwards like that.
我觉得在博卡奇卡 一切就像是这样反过来发生的
Now, right off the top here, I want to teach you guys one thing that's confusing.
那么 从这里开始 我想跟你们说一件让人迷惑的事情
Starship is the name of both the entire rocket as a whole.
Starship是整个火箭的名字
And also just the upper stage.
同时也只是上面级的名字
They're both Starship,
它们都是Starship
but Super Heavy is the first stage or the booster of the entire Starship system.
但超重是整个Starship系统的一级或者说助推器
So yes, it's confusing,
那么是的 这很容易混淆
but you'll hear me say Starship kind of meaning the whole system,
但我有可能会用Starship代指整个系统
but I might also be meaning just the upper stage.
也可能只是上面级
So just listen for context.
所以 要根据上下文判断
We should also point out here that Starship is a potential fleet of different vehicles.
我们还应该在这里指出 Starship是一个可能的一组不同的航天器
You might want to call it the Starship Launch System or SLS.
你可以叫它Starship发射系统或SLS
Wait, that's a thing.
等等 SLS好像(已经)是个东西了
Generally speaking in today's video, we'll be talking about a generic crew version,
大致上来说 在今天的视频中 我们会讨论一个通用的载人版本
载人Starship
能搭载大约100名乘客
目的地：月球，火星以及更远的地方
which we often see in the renders,
也就是经常在渲染图中看到的那个版本
but there's also a cargo version with a cargo bay
但也有带货舱的货运版
货运Starship
像张嘴一样的门
约1000立方米的可用体积
that opens its jaws like an alligator and releases massive, massive payloads.
这个版本像鳄鱼一样张开嘴 并且会释放出巨大的有效载荷
And there'll also be a tanker variant that only carries some additional propellant as its payload
还有一种储罐版 其有效载荷只是一些额外的推进剂
储罐Starship
用于在轨补加
in order to refuel other Starships already in orbit.
以便为其他已在轨道上的Starship补加推进剂
And we may someday see one way bound Starships that are stripped down
而也许有一天 我们会看到单程的乞丐版Starship
单程Starship
为深空任务而拆掉部件
没有气动特征或者再入设备
and only made to inject payloads to the outer Solar System.
而这只为了让有效载荷进入外太阳系
And there's also going to be that Lunar Lander version,
而且还会有那个月球着陆器的版本
登月Starship
NASA阿尔忒弥斯载人登月系统投标版
不会再入地球大气层
which will only stay in space in the earth moon system.
这只会停留在地月系统的太空中
And won't have the large flaps or heat shields,
而且不会有大襟翼和隔热板
and will also have additional landing engines,
并将增设着陆发动机
so they don't end up kicking up too much lunar regolith.
通过这种着陆发动机 (在着陆时) 飞船最终不会吹起太多的月球表面的土壤
Well, and then don't forget about the point to point version.
好吧 然后别忘了点对点的版本
地球运输版Starship
地球点对点运输
That might be a different iteration. That's just for Earth to Earth transportation.
这可能是一个不同的迭代版本 只用于地球到地球的运输
There could be just a whole new type of vehicle called Starship.
可能只是一种全新的交通工具 叫Starship
And this is literally just the beginning of that.
而这只是一个开始
So all this is to say Starship is still a bit in its development phase,
所以说 Starship还处于开发的早期阶段
but it is truly solidifying and maturing to the point where we can actually put all of this together for you,
但目前 它已经足够成熟到我可以把这些都讲给你听了
but do note things might change.
但请注意 事情可能会改变
Okay? Okay. So this is going to be a long video and like all my long videos,
好吗？ 好吧 这将是一个长视频 就像我所有的长视频一样
时间索引：05:05 - 有什么相同，06:00 - 有什么不同 // 发动机和燃料，
23:05 - 有什么不同 // 尺寸，运载能力，制造，花费，32:15 - 有什么不同 // 一级火箭重复使用，
41:50 - 有什么不同 // 二级火箭重复使用，53:40 - 总结
here's the timestamps which we also have in the description and the YouTube play bar is broken up as well.
这是时间戳 视频描述中也有 油管的进度条也分开了
www.everydayastronaut.com/definitive-guide-to-starship
There's also an article version for easy reading and searching at everydayastronaut.com.
还有一个文章版在everydayastronaut.com 方便阅读和搜索
有什么相同？
So before we start,
那么在我们开始之前
we might want to lay out what's the same between the Falcon 9 and Starship,
我们可能要列出猎鹰9号和Starship之间的相同之处
because that might be an easier place to start.
因为从这里开始讲会更容易一点
What's the same, uh, well, they're both rockets.
什么是相同的 呃 好吧 他们都是火箭
Uh, we can start there.
我们可以从那里开始
Both rockets have two stages.
两枚火箭都是两级构型
They both run on super chilled liquid fuels and have a reusable first stage with legs and grid fins.
都使用超低温液体燃料 同时其一级都带有着陆腿和栅格翼且可重复使用
They're both made by SpaceX.
这俩都是SpaceX制造的
They probably have virtually the same avionics and software,
这俩可能有几乎相同的飞控设备和软件
I think that's about it. Oh, they also have a, they each have a bunch of engines.
我想差不多就是这样 哦 还有一点相同 那就是都有一堆发动机
There we go. But I think that, I think that's literally it,
就这些 但我觉得不能再多了
I guess it's no wonder they stopped calling it the BFR or Big Falcon Rocket
难怪他们不叫它BFR或大猎鹰 火箭了
because Starship really has almost no Falcon heritage anymore.
因为Starship几乎真没有猎鹰的遗产了
Okay. Next.
好吧 下一个
有什么不同？
发动机和燃料
Where to begin, where to begin?
从哪里开始呢x2
Well, for starters, quite literally the heart of each rocket is its rocket engine
首先 对小白来说 每个火箭的心脏都是它的那台火箭发动机
or in this case, rocket engines
或者说 那些火箭发动机
because the Falcon 9, as the name suggests uses 9 Merlin 1D engines on the first stage
因为猎鹰9号顾名思义 就是指其一级使用了9台灰背隼1D发动机
and a single vacuum optimized Merlin called the M-Vac on the second stage.
和二级的单台真空优化的灰背隼发动机 被称为M-Vac
The Merlin engines are open cycle,
灰背隼发动机是开式循环的
meaning that they have a small baby rocket engine called a gas generator
这是指 其中包含一台像是小型的火箭发动机的燃气发生器
that burns just a little bit of fuel and a dash of LOX.
燃气发生器只燃烧一点儿的燃料和更少的液氧
And then that high energy exhaust hits a turbine.
燃烧后产生的高能量的废气带动涡轮
And that turbine then spins the main propellant pumps.
而涡轮则转动主推进剂泵
The exhaust from that process is simply dumped overboard like on the sea level Merlin,
比如海平面版灰背隼发动机 会把这个过程中产生的废气直接排掉
but on the vacuum Merlin, they actually route that exhaust gas back into the nozzle
但在真空灰背隼上 他们实际上是将废气送回喷管
这里指气膜冷却，但真空灰背隼不完全是气膜冷却
to help provide a layer of cooler gas to keep the nozzle extension from melting.
这样可以提供一层用于冷却的气体 来防止喷管延伸段融化
That's still crazy to me,
这对我来说还是很疯狂的
but SpaceX took everything to 11 when they decided to take on the most ambitious rocket engine ever made.
但SpaceX决定采用有史以来最难的火箭发动机
They developed an engine called the Raptor engine,
他们开发了一款名为伶盗龙的发动机
which is a full flow staged combustion cycle engine.
这是一台全流量分级燃烧循环发动机
The reason it's so complicated is
它之所以如此复杂 是因为
all of the exhaust gas that would normally be dumped overboard after spinning the turbine
通常情况下 所有涡轮泵排出的废气都会被直接排掉
is instead routed back into the main combustion chamber.
而是输送回主燃烧室
But not only that,
但不仅如此
there's two of those little rocket engines and two turbines and two pumps.
有两个小火箭发动机和两个涡轮和两个泵
And then both of their exhausts are pumped into the main combustion chamber.
然后它们的废气都会被注入到主燃烧室里
One of those is fuel rich and the other is oxygen rich.
其中一种是富燃废气 另一种是富氧废气
One little note here,
有一点要注意的是
if an engine is closed cycle where that exhaust gas is routed into the combustion chamber,
如果发动机是闭式循环 那么废气就会被输送到燃烧室
we will call the gas generator a preburner instead,
我们把这种气体发生器称为预燃器
since it's just pre-burning the fuel or the oxidizer or both.
因为它只是提前燃烧燃料或氧化剂 或两者都有
And it's then routed straight into the combustion chamber,
而后直接进入(主)燃烧室
despite extremely hot gaseous oxygen and wanting to turn every bit of the engine into soup,
尽管极热的气态氧 会想把发动机烧软成汤
having the fuel and the oxygen arrive in the combustion chamber as a hot gas adds a huge boost in efficiency,
但是 这样让燃料和氧气以热气的形式到达燃烧室 大大地提高了效率
or as Elon would say.
或者像马一龙说的那样
b23.tv/av70314372
[Elon] Certainly 98 and a half,
[马一龙] 当然有98.5%
hopefully 99% of theoretical combustion efficiency.
希望达到理论燃烧效率的99%
This is so if God himself came and knitted together, the molecules 1% better,
这个效率之高 以至于就算是上帝亲自来把分子织在一起
okay. Maybe one and a half percent better. That's all,
最多也就是比这个值高1%或者1.5%
that's very high efficiency cause [Tim] full flow [Elon] full flow staged combustion. Exactly.
这是非常高的效率 [Tim]这得益于全流量分级燃烧 [马一龙]全流量分级燃烧 没错
另外两种是集成动力验证器和RD-270，按照Tim的意思应该是RD-270制造出来过
This engine is so advanced that there's only ever been two other attempts at building one ever.
这款发动机是如此的先进 以至于只有另外两种尝试过制造 并且只有一种制造出来过
Neither of those engines would ever leave the test stand and fly.
这两种发动机都没有离开试车台进行过试飞
[Tim screaming like a child]
[Tim尖叫得像个孩子一样]
Yes! Oh my God! It's actually flying!!! *pants hath been pooped*.
爽 我的天啊 它真的飞起来了 *屎拉裤子上了*
这四次分别是Starshopper 20m，Starhopper 150m，SN5 150m，SN6 150m
And as of the making of this video, the Raptor has powered four short hops,
在这段视频的制作过程中 伶盗龙已经进行了四次短途跳跃
despite them never exceeding 150 meters.
尽管它们从未超过150米
It is the only time in history of full flow staged combustion cycle engine has been used to perform work,
这是历史上唯一一次采用全流量分级燃烧循环发动机来干活
but these hops were relatively simple.
但这些跳跃相对简单
Only a single engine sometimes offset from the center of the rocket,
只有一台发动机工作 而且有时才(安装得)偏离火箭的中心
like the prototype serial number five and serial number six,
像原型机序列号五和序列号六
but three engines is next for Starship for its first true flight
但Starship下一个真正意义上的首飞才会使用三台发动机
planning to reach 15 kilometers to practice its crazy landing sequence.
计划达到15公里 以实践其疯狂的降落过程
From there on out, the number of Raptors Starship will utilize will just keep on increasing.
从此以后 Starship将利用的伶盗龙数量只会不断增加
The orbital version of Starship will have three sea level Raptors and three large vacuum optimized Raptors,
轨道版的Starship将拥有3台海平面伶盗龙和3台大型真空优化伶盗龙
which are currently in development and beginning their testing, which is really exciting.
而这真空伶盗龙目前正在研制中 并正开展测试 这真的很令人兴奋
The Super Heavy booster will end up with over two dozen engines,
而超级重型助推器最终将配备二十多台发动机
eventually getting up to over 30 engines probably.
最终可能会达到三十多台发动机
Now this is all because of their relatively small size,
那么(能做到)这一切都是因为它们的体积比较小
SpaceX can squeeze tons of these Raptor engines on the bottom of the large rocket.
SpaceX可以在这样的大型火箭的底部挤上很多这种伶盗龙发动机
And don't worry, Starship shouldn't suffer from N1 syndrome.
而且也不用担心Starship会患上N1综合症
b23.tv/av925601122
People sometimes are quick to point out how using so many engines on the first stage is dumb
人们有时会很快指出 在一级使用这么多发动机是愚蠢的行为
because the Soviet Union's N1 moon rocket developed in the 1960s failed on all four of its launch attempts.
因为在20世纪60年代苏联研制的N1登月火箭 其四次发射尝试都失败了
Well, first off, don't forget the Falcon Heavy has had a perfect flight record and that thing uses 27 engines.
好吧 首先 别忘了重型猎鹰火箭曾有过完美的飞行记录 而那玩意用了27台发动机
So clearly the number of engines doesn't scare SpaceX,
所以很显然 发动机的数量并没有吓到SpaceX
but also the N1 failed for many reasons.
但N1的失败也有很多原因
Um, all of them really having very little to do with the actual number of engines.
嗯 所有的原因其实和实际的发动机数量关系都不大
In fact, having multiple engines is considered an advantage for the Falcon 9 and Falcon heavy
事实上 拥有多台发动机被认为是猎鹰9号和重型猎鹰的优势
because it allows for engine out capability.
因为拥有发动机故障熄火的冗余能力
This has proven useful
事实证明 这是有用的
on two flights where an engine has shut down on ascent,
特别是在两次飞行的上升段中都有一台发动机出现了熄火的情况
but the mission was still successful.
但任务仍然是成功的
Something that fewer engined rockets might not be able to do.
一些较少发动机的火箭可能做不到这件事
*火箭和发动机并未按照比例绘制
While we're talking about engines, we should mention the fuels each rocket runs on.
既然提到了发动机 我们就应该提到每枚火箭使用的燃料
The Falcon 9 runs on a rocket grade kerosene known as RP-1, along with liquid oxygen.
猎鹰9号使用的是一种被称为RP-1的航天级煤油 以及液氧
The combination is often referred to as Kerolox.
这种组合通常被称为Kerolox
Starship and its Raptor engines run on liquid methane and liquid oxygen, otherwise known as Methalox.
Starship及其伶盗龙发动机使用的是液态甲烷和液态氧 也就是所谓的Methalox
Liquid methane burns cleaner than RP-1 leaving behind virtually no soot in the engine.
液态甲烷比RP-1燃烧得更干净 几乎不会在发动机中留下残留物
It also has the potential to be more efficient,
它也有可能更有效率
but it is less dense than RP-1 which leads to slightly larger tanks by volume.
但它的密度比RP-1低 这就导致储罐的体积略大
One of the thing unique to SpaceX is in the constant pursuit of performance,
对SpaceX而言 独特之处在于 为了不断地追求性能
they began utilizing super chilled propellants on the Falcon 9 in 2015 with their first full thrust Falcon 9.
他们在2015年的第一枚全推力版猎鹰9号开始 在猎鹰9号上使用过冷推进剂
This means that they chill the RP-1 and the liquid oxygen more than any other operational rocket.
这意味着他们对RP-1和液氧的冷却程度超过了其他任何现役火箭
SpaceX chill their RP-1 from pretty much ambient temperature down about 30 degrees Celsius.
SpaceX将他们的RP-1从差不多是环境温度的低于30摄氏度左右
绝对零度
环境温度
So it ends up being below zero.
降低到零度以下(零下10度)
Burr.
But now that's not nothing compared to the liquid oxygen.
但这温度和液氧比起来 还不算什么
SpaceX chills, the liquid oxygen all the way down to minus 207 degrees Celsius,
SpaceX把液氧一路降到零下207摄氏度
which is only 12 degrees away from freezing solid.
这离凝固点只有12度
Although they likely gotten too far into super chilling propellant for the Raptor engine,
虽然他们很可能在伶盗龙发动机上也使用超低温推进剂
it is in the works.
但这仍在研制中
But by default liquid methane is very close in temperature to liquid oxygen.
但默认情况下 液态甲烷与液态氧的温度非常接近
It's boiling point is minus 161.5 degrees Celsius,
液态甲烷的沸点是零下161.5摄氏度
and it becomes a solid at minus 182 degrees Celsius.
并在零下182摄氏度时变成固体
So we'll likely see
那么我们可能会看到
SpaceX chill there methane down closer to minus 180 degrees Celsius as the engine develops,
随着发动机的发展 SpaceX会将甲烷冷却到接近零下180摄氏度的水平
and as they continue to squeeze performance out of that beast.
而这样才能继续榨取这野兽的性能
Now, if you can get to know all about the full flow staged combustion cycle
现在 如果你想搞清楚这些知识 比如全流量分级燃烧循环
and other cycles and why they use methane,
还有其他循环 以及为什么他们使用甲烷
b23.tv/av57059171
be sure and watch my video all about the Raptor engine
请务必观看我那个关于伶盗龙发动机的视频
so you can understand the cycle better and the trade-offs of using methane.
这样你就可以更好地理解发动机循环方式 以及在使用甲烷上的权衡
But there's more than just a fuel and oxidizer tank inside each stage of these rockets.
但这些火箭的每一级都不止有燃料和氧化剂罐
And here's where the Falcon 9 is more complex than Starship
而猎鹰9号比Starship更复杂的地方在这里
because it has three additional consumables on board stored inside smaller tanks.
因为其箭上还有三种消耗品储存在较小的储罐内
Inside Each oxygen tank of the Falcon 9 is a set of composite overwrapped pressure vessels or COPVs
在猎鹰9号的每个氧气罐内 都有一套缠绕复合材料压力容器或COPV
that house compressed helium.
COPV中存储着压缩氦气
And when I say compressed helium, I mean compressed,
这氦气压缩得老厉害了
we're talking 380 plus bar in these bottles.
压了足足380多巴
They use these to maintain constant pressure in the propellant tanks of about three to four bar.
他们用这些来保持推进剂罐中大约三到四巴的压力
So as the fuel drains out, they put helium in its place,
所以当燃料排出时 他们把氦气填入
which is extremely un-dense or not dense.
而氦气是密度很低的
And that ends up filling the void and maintain sufficient pressure.
而这最终填补了空隙 并保持足够的压力
And it's inert so it's not explosive.
而且氦气是惰性的 所以不会爆炸
Starship might eventually do away with these almost entirely.
Starship最终可能会几乎完全不要这些东西
The likely always needs some COPVs to store helium to spin start the Raptors,
Starship可能总是需要一些氦气COPV 以转动(涡轮来启动)伶盗龙
but SpaceX will be utilizing something called autogenous pressurization of the propellant tanks.
但SpaceX将使用一种叫做推进剂罐的自生增压技术
While the engines are running, they'll be pumping some higher pressure fuel or oxidizer
当发动机运行时 通过这种技术把一些高压燃料或氧化剂注入
气态再加压管路
back into their respective tanks to maintain proper pressure.
回到各自的储罐中以保持适当的压力
主液氧储罐
主甲烷储罐
The Space Shuttle did the same thing,
航天飞机也是这样做的
but once they're in space, they're going to maintain their pressure
但一旦Starship进入太空 就会保持储罐的压力
by allowing some of the fuel to boil off and then release any excess pressure.
也就是通过让部分燃料沸腾 之后再释放多余的压力
And of course, temperature and pressure are directly related due to the laws of thermodynamics.
当然 由于热力学定律 温度和压力是直接相关的
So by releasing pressure, it also helps maintain their temperature
所以通过释放压力 也有助于维持温度
and they can store propellant in smaller tanks,
而且他们可以把推进剂储存在较小的罐子里
which are inside the main tanks and these are called header tanks.
这些小罐子在主罐内 被称为头罐(头部储罐)
液氧头部储罐
甲烷头部储罐
Since they're going to be inside of another tank,
由于头罐外面有另一个储罐
the propellant will receive almost no heat from the sun and therefore it shouldn't boil off.
推进剂几乎不会收到太阳的热量 因此不会沸腾
There's another reason for those header tanks.
而头罐存在的另一个原因是
They're kind of reserved tanks in a sense, mostly for the landing phase.
某种意义上 它们是用于着陆的备用储罐
We'll talk about this more in a minute,
我们稍后再谈这个问题
but Starship will do some pretty intense maneuvers.
但Starship会做一些非常激烈的机动
Starship降落时，储罐部分会是空的
And if it tried to light its engines from a partially empty tank,
如果它想从部分是空的储罐中(抽取燃料并)点燃发动机
it would suck up air bubbles, which would destroy the engine.
它吸入的气泡会破坏发动机
So these header tanks just provide a source of propellant that's on tap,
所以 这些头罐的存在只是让推进剂随时可用
no matter the orientation or G load of the rocket.
无论火箭或G载荷的方向如何
But one interesting thing about Starship is its tanks will be at a higher pressure overall than the Falcon 9.
但Starship的一个有趣之处在于 它的储罐整体压力比猎鹰9号更高
They'll maintain more like five or six bar instead of three or four.
它们会保持5到6巴的压力 而不是3到4巴
Isn't it honestly super weird to think that
说实话 是不是让人觉得很奇怪？
when a rocket like the Falcon 9 is fully fueled up and pressurized for flight,
当猎鹰9号这样的火箭完全加满燃料并为飞行加压时
there's more pressure inside of that rocket than a car tire
火箭里面的压力比汽车轮胎里的还要大
and Starship will have almost twice as much pressure as that when it's pressed for flight.
而Starship在飞行时的压力几乎是它的两倍
That's honestly just crazy to me.
说实话 这对我来说实在是太疯狂了
Another thing the Falcon 9 has that Starship won't have is ignition fluid.
猎鹰9号还有一个Starship没有的东西就是点火液
The Falcon 9 uses what's known as TEA-TEB or Triethylaluminum - Triethylborane,
猎鹰9号使用的是所谓的TEA-TEB或三乙基铝-三乙基硼烷
which is a pyrophoric mixture.
这是一种可自燃的混合物
This means it'll instantly combust, when it comes in contact with oxygen.
这是指 它与氧气接触时 会立即燃烧
As SpaceX gets the pumps spinning up on the Falcon 9,
当SpaceX在猎鹰9号上启动泵的时候
they inject TEA-TEB into the combustion chamber to initiate combustion
他们会将TEA-TEB注入燃烧室来开始点火
while they begin to dump fuel and then get it into a stable combustion state.
与此同时 就开始泵出燃料 然后使其进入稳定的燃烧状态
This is important to be able to restart the Merlin engines with an onboard starting fluid
这对于能重新点火的灰背隼发动机而言 能使用箭上点火液是非常重要的
so they can relight some of the engines two or three times during its reentry and landing process.
这样他们就可以在返回和着陆过程中重新点燃某些发动机两到三次
Now without TEA-TEB, the engines would fail to reignite.
那么如果没有TEA-TEB 发动机将无法重新点火
If you look closely before any Merlin engine ignition,
如果你在任何灰背隼发动机点火前 仔细观察
you might actually catch the green flash from the TEA-TEB.
你可能真的能看到TEA-TEB的绿色闪光
And again, just like with helium, you can't exactly refill your TEA-TEB bottles on Mars.
而同样地 就像氦气一样 在火星上也不能重新装满TEA-TEB瓶
So for Starship and Raptor engines, they're utilizing a spark ignition.
所以Starship和伶盗龙的发动机采用的是火花点火法
I think this is quite literally like a giant spark plug
我想这就像一个巨大的火花塞一样
or basically a freaking arc welder that begins the ignition process.
或基本上是个特别的电弧焊机 来开始点火过程
But there's one more propellant SpaceX uses on the Falcon 9
但SpaceX在猎鹰9号上还使用了一种推进剂
and that's cold gas or compressed nitrogen, basically just compressed air.
那就是冷气或压缩氮气 基本上就是压缩空气
Since nitrogen is 78% of the air we breathe.
因为氮气占我们呼吸的空气的78%
They utilize compressed nitrogen for the cold gas thrusters on the interstage of Falcon 9,
猎鹰9号级间段的冷气推进器使用压缩氮气
the part between the first and second stage.
级间段就是一级和二级之间的部分
There's two packs of four little thrusters sitting way up there on top of the booster.
有两个由四个小推进器组成的装置 放在助推器的顶部
These are there to help it flip around and continue to point and guide the booster as it coasts before reentry.
在再入前的滑行段中 这些推进器可以帮助助推器翻转 并继续引导助推器
And just like before, there's not as much nitrogen on Mars,
就像前面所说的一样 火星上没有那么多的氮气
but even more so SpaceX doesn't want to have to carry around a separate propellant
但更重要的是 SpaceX不希望再多携带一种的推进剂
if they don't really have to.
如果他们真的没有必要的话
So instead Starship will actually utilize brand new hot gas thrusters
所以Starship将使用全新的热气推进器
that are powered by gaseous methane and gaseous oxygen.
由气态甲烷和气态氧提供动力
We don't really know too much about these new thrusters,
我们对这些新的推进器还不太了解
这是本期视频某些专有名词翻译标准调整的原因
but knowing SpaceX they'll probably be named after a bird.
但在了解SpaceX之后 他们可能会以鸟的名字命名
So all in all the different fuels, different cycle types, different sizes,
所以总的来说不同的燃料 不同的循环类型 不同的尺寸
and all other considerations leads to pretty drastic upgrades in performance for the power plant of each rocket.
和其他所有的考虑因素 都给火箭的发动机性能带来了相当大的提升
SpaceX's Merlin engine reaches an impressive amount of thrust at 845 kilonewtons at sea level
SpaceX的灰背隼发动机在海平面上达到了845千牛顿的惊人推力
and 981 kilonewtons in a vacuum,
而真空中则有981千牛顿
but the Raptor engine is currently in its infancy
但伶盗龙发动机目前还处于研制的初期
and running at around 1,650 kilonewtons at sea level
其海平面推力约为1650千牛顿
and can achieve probably somewhere around 1800 kilonewtons in a vacuum,
并能在真空中大概达到1800千牛顿左右
but they've already achieved just above 2000 kilonewtons of thrust on the stand.
但他们已经在试车台上实现了刚刚超过2000千牛顿的推力
And that will be their operating thrust relatively soon.
而这很快将成为他们的实用推力
And there's another more powerful variant coming.
还有另一个更强大的种类即将到来
Someday there's going to be a non deep-throttling booster variant of Raptor
总有一天 伶盗龙会有一个非深度节流的用于助推器的种类
that'll be on the outer ring of the booster
这会用在(超重)助推器的外圈(发动机)上
and they're targeting closer to 3000 kilonewtons of thrust at sea level
他们的目标是海平面推力接近3000千牛顿
and more like 3,200 kilonewtons of thrust in a vacuum.
而真空推力达到近3200千牛顿
Wow. I mean, after all
哇 我是指 毕竟
the Merlin has had every single last drop of performance squeezed out of it after over a decade of continuously developing the engine
在十多年不停地开发之下 灰背隼发动机的性能已经被榨干得一滴不剩
and the Raptor is just in its infancy.
而伶盗龙只是处于起步阶段
Next up efficiency.
接下来是效率
Now this is measured in specific impulse or ISP.
那么 这是以比冲或ISP来衡量的
The higher, the number, the better kind of like the gas mileage or fuel efficiency of a car.
数字越高越好 有点像汽车的同油耗行驶距离或燃油效率
The Merlin is pretty darn efficient,
灰背隼的效率很高(相比于RS-27)
achieving 282 seconds of specific impulse at sea level and 311 seconds in a vacuum.
海平面比冲为282秒 真空比冲为311秒
But the Raptor engine is even more efficient currently achieving 325 seconds at sea level
但伶盗龙发动机的效率更高 目前在海平面上达到325秒
and close to 350 seconds in a vacuum.
并在真空中接近350秒
A lot of this performance is due to the chamber pressure inside the main combustion chamber.
这种性能(的提升)很大程度上是归功于主燃烧室内部的腔室压力
The higher the chamber pressure,
燃烧室压力越大
the more potential the rocket has to turn that high pressure into higher thrust and better efficiency too.
火箭就有更大的潜力将这样的高压转化为更大的推力和更好的效率
The Merlin achieves 116 bar of pressure while the Raptor is operationally at around 275 bar currently,
灰背隼的压力为116巴 而伶盗龙目前的可用压力约为275巴
but it's hit 330 bar on the test stand
但它在测试台上达到了330巴的压力
and it will likely reach their goal of 350 bar operationally before too long,
并且很可能在不久之后 就会达到他们之前竖立的实用压力目标 350巴
knowing SpaceX.
你懂得 这可是SpaceX
But at the end of the day, there is one metric where Merlin currently outperforms the Raptor.
但归根结底 目前灰背隼有一个指标是优于伶盗龙的
That's thrust to weight ratio.
那就是推重比
The Merlin will be hard to beat
灰背隼将很难被击败
because it has the highest thrust to weight ratio of any liquid fueled rocket engine ever.
因为它的推重比是有史以来液体燃料火箭发动机中最高的
The Merlin engine has a nutty thrust to weight ratio of around 200 to 1.
灰背隼发动机的疯狂推重比约为200比1
While the Raptor currently is around 107 to 1,
而伶盗龙目前的推重比约为107比1
but increasing to 130 to one.
但会增加到130比1
And again, Elon thinks they can get it to match the Merlin someday,
而一样的 马一龙认为他们有朝一日能让它追上灰背隼
but perhaps one metric that's just as important,
但也许有一个指标同样重要
especially when you're cramming, dozens of engines inside of a fixed area
特别是当你在一个固定的区域里面塞进 几十个发动机的时候
is thrust to engine footprint ratio.
这就是推力与发动机的占地面积比
You may notice that the Raptor isn't that much wider or take up that much more space than the Merlin.
你可能会注意到 伶盗龙并不比灰背隼宽那么多 也不比灰背隼多占那么多空间
And especially when you factor in the entire footprint of the engine.
尤其是当你把整个发动机的占地面积考虑进去的时候
Notice that the Merlin has that large gas generator exhaust just sticking way off on the side of the engine
请注意 灰背隼有那个大的气体发生器排气管正好伸出在发动机的一侧
while the Raptor almost fits inside its own footprint.
而伶盗龙的外形几乎可以装进自己的占位面积内
This stuff matters when you're cramming tons of engines together.
当你把很多的发动机挤在一起时 这个参数就很重要
So when it's all said and done
那么 总的来说
*火箭和发动机并未按照比例绘制
the first stage of the Falcon 9 with its 9 engines achieved 7.6 mega Newtons of thrust.
猎鹰9号一级的9个发动机实现了7.6兆牛顿的推力
Falcon Heavy, which is currently the most powerful rocket flying gets 22.8 mega Newtons.
而重型猎鹰火箭 作为目前最强大的现役火箭 其推力为22.8兆牛顿
And Starship's Super Heavy Booster will end up with... Ready for this?
而Starship的超级重型助推器最终会达到……准备好了吗？
About three times the thrust of that at 65 mega Newtons.
三倍于它的推力 即65兆牛顿
That's likely going to be about the minimum thrust we'll see for an operational orbital version.
而这可能是实用化的轨道版Starship的最低推力了
But it'll probably increase
但推力可能会增加
when they start utilizing more engines or those more powerful booster variants on the outer ring.
在他们使用更多发动机 或者在外圈上采用那些更强大的助推器专用发动机的时候
Okay. I know what you might be thinking right now.
好吧 我知道你现在可能在想什么
Why didn't they just put the Raptor engine and test it out on the Falcon 9?
为什么他们不把伶盗龙发动机放在猎鹰9号上测试呢？
Could they, uh, technically, maybe yes.
技术上 呃 他们也许可以这么做
And it was kind of looked at for an upper stage variant for a Falcon Heavy,
而且可以作为一种 用于重型猎鹰的修改版上面级(的发动机)
but really by the time you do that, it wouldn't be worth it at all,
但真正到了你要这样做的时候 就完全不值得了
If you were to put, say, just a Raptor engine as an upper stage for Falcon 9 or Falcon Heavy,
如果你要把伶盗龙发动机作为猎鹰9号或重型猎鹰的上面级
you'd have to redesign the whole upper stage because now it has to handle a lot higher loads
你必须重新设计整个上面级 因为现在它必须能处理更高的负荷
because don't forget it's over twice as powerful.
因为别忘了 伶盗龙的推力是原来的两倍多
The Merlin vacuum is already too powerful
而灰背隼真空发动机已经太强大了
and it has to throttle way down to be able to not smash all of its things it's trying to put up into space.
而且它还得进行节流才不会把载荷都摧毁了
And of course you couldn't put 9 Raptor engines inside the same diameter of a Falcon 9
当然 你也不可能把9个伶盗龙发动机 放在直径不变的猎鹰9号上
because they wouldn't fit.
因为这根本放不下
So you couldn't. You could maybe do like three or four,
你可也许可以放下3-4台伶盗龙发动机
but now you don't have a good way to have a landing engine.
但这样着陆发动机就有点不合适了
Your forces are totally different.
而且(箭体)的受力完全不同
Your bulkheads are different because of the different densities of fuel.
舱壁也不同 因为燃料密度不同
All of this, it would basically, it would be a totally different rocket.
总而言之 (换发后的猎鹰9号)实际上会变得完全不同
And if you're building a new rocket anyway, why not go big?
而且如果你都要造一个新火箭了 为什么不做大呢？
Well, they did that exact same thing with the Falcon 1.
好吧 他们在猎鹰1号上做了相同的事情
People thought it was crazy.
人们觉得这是疯狂的
They weren't just upgrading their Falcon 1 and flying it more
当它们不只是升级并继续发射猎鹰1号
and that they were going to be jumping to the Falcon 9.
甚至直接跳到猎鹰9号
But in hindsight, it's a really good thing they didn't sink one more dollar into the Falcon 1,
不过现在看来 他们没有在猎鹰1号上多扔一块钱 真是一件好事
and it's a good thing they moved on to a bigger and better rocket, the Falcon 9.
他们转到了猎鹰9号这枚更大更好的火箭上 也是一件好事
And now SpaceX is doing this all over again.
而现在SpaceX又重新这样做了
And if you're starting over with a totally fresh design, you might as well go bigger.
而如果你要开始一个全新的设计 可能就会做得更大
I mean a lot bigger.
我是指 大很多
有什么不同？
尺寸，运载能力，制造，花费
Okay, next they're sizes. Starship is massive.
好吧 接下来是尺寸 Starship是巨大的
Like really, really big.
非常非常大
Now don't get me wrong.
那么别误会我的意思
The Falcon 9 is actually quite a decent sized rocket,
猎鹰9号其实(已经)是个大火箭了
and it's really hard to appreciate just how big it actually is until you're standing underneath it.
如果不是站在火箭下面 你真的很难体会到它到底有多大
But at 9 meters wide compared to the Falcon 9's 3.7 meters wide,
但9米的宽度与猎鹰9号的3.7米宽度相比
the Falcon 9 is narrow enough to be transported cross country by road.
猎鹰9号是可以窄到用陆路横跨全国进行运输
But Starship, not so much.
但Starship 就不一样了
Although it does get transported by road,
虽然它确实可以通过公路运输
it only does a little tiny bit on a completely closed off highway in Boca Chica, Texas.
但只能在德克萨斯州博卡奇卡的一条完全封闭的高速公路上进行一点点距离的移动
The Falcon 9 stands 70 meters tall with its first age at 45 meters tall
猎鹰9号高70米 一级高45米
while the second stage and the nose cone or fairing as we call it comprise the other 25 meters.
而二级和我们所说的鼻锥或整流罩则由另外25米组成
Despite being pretty tall,
尽管很高
The entire Falcon 9 will be able to fit inside just the Super Heavy booster.
整个猎鹰9号只需超级重型助推器就能装进去
The Super Heavy booster will stand over 72 meters tall, likely closer to 75 meters tall.
超级重型助推器的高度将超过72米 很可能接近75米高
Then put the Starship upper stage on top of the Super Heavy Booster
然后把Starship上面级放在超级重型助推器的上面
and the entire stack will stand 122 meters tall.
而这么一摞将高达122米
That's over 10 meters taller than the monster Saturn V.
这比怪物土星五号还要高10多米
Yep. That's right. It'll be about as tall as a 35 story building.
没错 就是这样 它的高度将和一栋35层楼一样高
In fact, it'll pretty much be exactly as tall as the tallest skyscraper-esque condominiums on nearby South Padre Island,
事实上 它的高度和旁边的南帕德雷岛的最高的摩天大楼式公寓一样高
the Sapphire South Padre, which stands 123 meters tall.
也就是南帕德雷蓝宝石 高123米
And once you put Starship up on its massive launch mount,
而一旦你把Starship放在它那巨大的发射架上
it will be the tallest thing for hundreds of kilometers.
它会是数百公里内最高的东西
Yeah. Just wait until that thing takes off.
是啊 等着看那东西起飞吧
I think it's going to melt a few brains and probably break a few windows.
我觉得这个景象会烧坏一些人的脑子 并可能打破几个窗户
Couple, this massive size with their different engines, with different performance figures and different fuels.
再加上 这巨大的尺寸以及不同的发动机 不同的性能数据和不同的燃料
And what it all means is Starship can put a lot bigger and heavier things into orbit.
而这一切都意味着Starship可以将大得多也重得多的东西送入轨道
*火箭和发动机并未按照比例绘制
The Falcon 9 can take 22,800 kilograms into low earth orbit when it's expended
猎鹰9号可以把22.8吨的东西送入低地轨道(LEO)
or 15,600 kilograms, when reused like it does for the Starlink missions.
如果像星链发射任务那样重复使用的话 就是15.6吨
It can send 8,300 kilograms on a geostationary transfer orbit, when expended
而不回收的情况下 地球静止转移轨道(GTO)运力为8.3吨
or around 7,000 kilograms when reused.
或者回收时约为7吨(应该是亚GTO)
Now let's drop in Falcon Heavy,
那么让我们把重型猎鹰扔进去
which can take between 63,800 kilograms when fully expended
不回收时LEO运力为63.8吨
and about 27,500 kilograms with two cores returning to the launch site and one core landing on the drone ship.
助推器返场回收而芯级海上无人船回收的情况下 LEO运力为27.5吨
Falcon Heavy can even get about 25,000 kilograms to geostationary transfer orbit one fully expended,
不回收时 GTO运力为25吨
but it still gets about 9,500 kilograms when doing the two core on land one core and the drone ship.
助推器返场回收而芯级海上无人船回收的情况下 GTO运力为9.5吨
But Starship will be able to take over 150,000 kilograms to low-earth orbit.
但Starship将能带着超过150吨的质量进入低地轨道
Yeah, that'll be more payload mass than any rocket ever made,
是啊 这将是比任何火箭都要多的(LEO)有效载荷质量
土五的LEO运力应该参考其两级版衍生型土星INT-21的运力116吨，而不是三级版中加上三级质量的145吨，
来源www.astronautix.com/s/saturnint-21.html
even beating out the Saturn V, which could only put 145,000 kilograms into low earth orbit.
甚至击败了土星五号 后者只能将145吨的重物送入低地轨道
Starship can also put a solid 21,000 kilograms out to a geostationary transfer orbit
Starship也能把21吨的重物送入GTO轨道
despite having to lug its own huge dry mass around there.
尽管它必须拖着自己巨大的干质量到那里
So yes, it's lower than an expendable Falcon Heavy, which is over a hundred million dollars.
那么是的 它比超过一亿美元的消耗性的重型猎鹰的GTO运力要低
But if you expended a Super Heavy Booster, it would easily exceed that.
但如果消耗一个超级重型助推器 会很容易就会超过这个数字
But expending a Super Heavy is just simply not in the plans.
但这样的打法根本不在计划之内
Don't forget, since the whole rocket is reusable,
别忘了 既然整个火箭是可以重复使用的
Starship has to take its heavy flaps, landing gear, the payload fairing,
Starship要得要带上它的重重的翼面 着陆腿 整流罩
and all six engines with it everywhere it goes.
以及六台发动机
So instead, here's where Starship can make up for that with orbital refueling.
所以 Starship可以用推进剂在轨补加来弥补运力损失
If Starship is refueled with just one tanker,
如果Starship只用一艘储罐版飞船来进行推进剂补加
it can get that GTO payload capacity right back up to 150,000 kilograms.
它可以让GTO运载能力恢复到150吨
And if you refuel it enough,
如果你给它加满推进剂
it can actually take 150,000 kilograms all the way to the moon or Mars.
它实际上可以带着150吨的载荷去月球或火星
That is game-changing.
这改变了游戏规则
Another huge upgrade for Starship is it's massive payload Bay.
Starship的另一个巨大升级是它那巨大的有效载荷舱
The Falcon 9 and Falcon Heavy shared the same fairing,
猎鹰9号和重型猎鹰共用同一个整流罩
which is about 5 meters wide and 14 meters tall with a total usable volume of 145 cubic meters.
宽约5米 高约14米 总可用容积为145立方米
Although there is an extended version coming soon that is taller
虽然很快就会有更高的加长版
and will get the volume closer to 200 cubic meters.
并将使体积接近200立方米
But Starship's payload bay is a whopping 9 meters wide
但Starship的有效载荷舱宽度高达9米
and 18 meters high with a usable volume of around a thousand cubic meters.
有18米高 可用容积约1000立方米
Yep. That's more pressurized volume than a 747
是的 这比747飞机的加压容积还要大
and there's an extended payload version coming soon that's 22 meters in height.
还有一个即将推出的加长版 高度为22米
Another big difference is what these rockets are made out of.
另一个最大的区别是这些火箭的材质
The Falcon 9 is made out of 2219 aluminum alloy and some carbon composite
猎鹰9号是由2219铝合金和一些碳纤维复合材料制成的
while Starship is made out of stainless steel 304L
而Starship则是由304L不锈钢制成的
and will eventually be made out of a SpaceX in-house developed 30X stainless steel.
并最终将由SpaceX内部研发的30X不锈钢制成
Now aluminum is typically the lighter option,
那么铝材是典型的轻量化选项
but only really at cryogenic temperatures.
但真的只能适用于低温的情况下
But the reason for using stainless steel on Starship is
但在Starship上使用不锈钢的原因在于
because it not only needs to handle low cryogenic temperatures,
它不仅需要处理低温
but it also needs to handle re-entry heat for both stages.
但它还需要处理火箭的两个分级上的再入热
Falcon 9 actually has some heat shielding on the octoweb,
猎鹰9号其实在八个一圈上有一些热屏蔽措施
which is the bottom of the booster that holds all the engines.
八个一圈是指助推器容纳了所有的发动机的底部
This keeps the extreme heat of reentry from destroying the fuselage.
这样可以防止再入时的极热破坏箭体
Because of Starship's stainless steel construction,
由于Starship的不锈钢结构
they're hoping to not require any additional heat shielding on the Super Heavy booster,
他们希望在超级重型助推器上不需要任何额外的热屏蔽
but the upper stage of Starship will need to employ additional heat shielding tiles
但Starship的上面级将需要采用额外的隔热瓦
along its windward side or its belly when it's reentering from orbital velocity.
这些隔热瓦处在它的腹部 也就是从轨道再入时的迎风面
Now we'll talk about this a little bit more in a second,
那么 我们待会再谈这个问题
but had they gone with another material,
但如果他们用其他材料
it would have required even bigger and heavier heat shielding.
就需要更大更重的热屏蔽
Originally SpaceX wanted to use carbon fiber for Starship,
原本SpaceX想用碳纤维来做Starship
but maybe one of the biggest reasons they switched to stainless steel is
但也许他们改用不锈钢的最大原因之一是
so they could rapidly prototype the vehicle.
这样可以快速地制造出航天器的原型
They can construct, make changes to and iterate on a stainless steel Starship
他们可以在不锈钢的Starship上建造 修改并迭代
with simple construction methods and do it really cheap too.
通过简单的施工方法来实现 而且做起来也很便宜
We're not really going to get into the philosophy
我们并不是真的要在这个视频里去研究这种(研发的)哲学
of this iterative and quick design, building, manufacturing and prototyping process in this video
这种可迭代和快速的设计 制造和原型制作过程的哲学
b23.tv/av285667766
because we've covered it very much in depth in the SLS versus Starship video already,
因为我们已经在SLS与Starship的视频中深入介绍过了
but maybe the most unique bit of hardware are those giant flippity flappidiy finny Airbrake things on Starship,
但也许最独特的设备是Starship上那些巨大的可以翻转的像空气刹车一样的东西
or as I call them Elonerons.
或者我称他们为马翼龙
Now, yes, these are something entirely new.
那么 没错 这是全新的翼面
They're a unique control scheme that will help the vehicle maintain control while reentering belly first.
这是一种独特的控制方案 有助于在再入时 航天器腹部迎风姿态下 保持控制
These Elonerons will basically be powered by some Tesla electric motors with a direct drive,
这些马翼龙基本上将由一些特斯拉电动机直接驱动
despite requiring insane amounts of torque geared the right way,
尽管需要疯狂的扭矩往正确的方向摆动
that's something an electric motor has plenty of.
而电动机就有着足够的扭矩
And they'll be powered by Tesla batteries too, or at least derived from them.
而且它们也会由特斯拉电池及其衍生品提供动力
And for longer missions, Starship will have solar panels.
而对于更长时间的任务 Starship会有太阳能电池板
Now we don't have too much info on that yet,
关于这个 现在我们还没有太多的信息
but they'll definitely work their way into designs.
但它们一定会在设计中发挥作用
But this is all just a giant iterative phase.
但这一切只是一个巨大的迭代阶段
SpaceX is making a huge and powerful rocket, but what's it all for.
SpaceX正在制造一个巨大而强大的火箭 但这一切是为了什么
Forget the size of Starship.
先不说Starship的大小
The economics of this rocket is probably the biggest thing.
这枚火箭的经济性可能是最大的问题
Now we're not really going to get into this pricing too much
现在我们并不打算过多地讨论这个定价问题
because we've talked about that a lot in other videos,
因为我们在其他视频中已经说了很多
but I just wanted to talk about price kind of generally
但我只是想大概地谈谈价格
to help put into perspective how game-changing Starship could be.
以帮助人们认识到Starship可能会改变游戏规则
And of course, only time will tell what the true cost of everything actually will be.
当然 一切的真实成本究竟是多少 只有时间才能验证
Despite being able to take almost 10 times as much payload into orbit as the Falcon 9
尽管能够将几乎10倍于猎鹰9号的有效载荷质量送入轨道
Starship should cost less than the Falcon 9 to launch.
Starship的发射成本应该比猎鹰9号更低
In fact, because it's fully reusable,
事实上 因为它完全可重复使用
it should basically only be the cost of fuel and personnel time.
成本基本上应该只是燃料和人员时间
But we're talking about potentially way less than a Falcon 9.
但这可能比猎鹰9号少得多
SpaceX is hoping it will cost less to launch than their Falcon 1 even.
SpaceX希望它的发射成本甚至比猎鹰1号还要低
I mean, in fact, it very well might end up being the cheapest ride to orbit period.
我是指 它真的很有可能最终成为最便宜的入轨方式
No matter the payload.
无论是什么有效载荷
In other words, it could be so cheap to launch an entire Starship
换句话说 发射一整艘Starship都可能如此便宜
that you could put, just say, a smallsat or a couple of cubesats or something tiny on it.
你可以在上面放一个小卫星或几个立方星或一些小东西
And it might be cheaper than launching on say an Electron rocket or some other smallsat launcher.
这可能比用电子火箭或其他小型卫星运载火箭的发射更便宜
And that my friends is why Starship is truly revolutionary compared to even the Falcon 9.
而老铁汁们 这就是为什么Starship比起猎鹰9号都要革命性的原因
But in order to fulfill that goal, Starship will have to be reusable, fully and rapidly reusable.
但是为了实现这个目标Starship必须是完全可以快速重复使用的
So just how exactly can it do that?
那么究竟如何才能做到这一点呢？
What hardware is different, that's going to make that dream happen?
采用什么不一样的设备 才能实现这个梦想呢？
有什么不同？
一级火箭重复使用
And for the coolest part, or at least my favorite part, reuse.
而最帅的部分 至少是我最喜欢的部分 则是重复使用
After all there's nothing more exciting than watching a rocket land in person,
毕竟没有什么比亲眼看着火箭降落更让人兴奋的了
falling from the sky, igniting its engines at what feels like the last possible second
从天而降 直到感觉像是可能允许着陆的最后一秒才点燃发动机
and landing under a precise column of flames
并在一道火柱之下 着陆
and Starship is going to be taking this up a notch.
而Starship要在这个基础上更上一层楼
After all the Falcon 9 has set a new bar in the aerospace industry
毕竟猎鹰9号已经在航天领域树立了新的标杆
by propulsively landing the first stage and reusing it.
通过反推式着陆一级并重复使用
As of the making of this video,
截至本视频制作时
nearly half of all Falcon 9s that have ever flown have used a booster that's flown more than once.
有史以来飞行的猎鹰9号中 其中近一半都使用了飞行过一次以上的助推器
And what SpaceX developed for the Falcon 9 and the Falcon Heavy's booster is clearly working out great.
而显然 SpaceX为猎鹰9号和重型猎鹰的助推器所开发的东西效果很好
And it's actually a very similar method they'll use for the Super Heavy Boosters.
而超级重型助推器也会使用非常类似的东西
So let's follow the first stages
那么 让我们先讲讲一级
and talk about all the systems and the hardware in play and how it all works.
并说说所有系统和设备的作用 以及它们是如何运作的
Of course, at liftoff, all engines will ignite on both rockets.
当然 升空时 两枚火箭的所有发动机都会点火
As soon as the computer senses, the engines are up and running smoothly and at full thrust,
只要电脑完成(传感器的)记录 发动机就会启动 并以全推力平稳运行
it'll command the launchpad to let go.
它将命令发射台释放牵制释放装置
Both rockets will ascend mostly vertically at first
两枚火箭一开始都会以垂直方向上升
to get out of the thickest parts of the atmosphere as quickly as possible.
以期尽快离开大气层最厚的地方
But shortly after takeoff,
但起飞后不久
they'll begin to pitch over horizontally in the direction of their desired orbit.
它们将开始向所需的轨道方向水平转向
By stage separation they'll pretty much be entirely horizontal
到了分离阶段 它们就会几乎完全水平了
giving the upper stage as much horizontal velocity as they can possibly spare.
给予末级尽可能多的水平速度
Let's assume both first stages are going to be heading back to the launch site.
我们假设这俩一级都要返回发射场
Otherwise known as return to launch site or RTLS.
也就是所谓的返回发射场(机动)或RTLS
The Falcon 9 only can do this for fairly lightweight, low earth orbit missions,
猎鹰9号只有在相当轻量级的LEO任务中才能做到这一点
but Super Heavy will likely always return to the launch site
但超重助推器很可能总会返回发射场
like the actual launch complex, not a separate landing complex.
是真正的返场回收 而不是一个单独的着陆场
In order to get back to the launch site,
为了回到发射场
the boosters need to cancel out their horizontal velocity as quickly as possible
助推器需要尽快地抵消其水平速度
because at stage separation, they're traveling at thousands of kilometers an hour away from the launchpad.
因为在分级时 它们正以每小时数千公里的速度远离发射台
This is called the boost back burn.
这就是所谓的助推返场点火
The Falcon 9 lights up three of its 9 Merlin engines,
猎鹰9号会点燃9个灰背隼发动机中的3个
but Super Heavy will likely light up all of its center engines.
但超重型很可能会点燃其所有的中心发动机
Not only do they need to cancel out the horizontal velocity,
不但要抵消水平速度
they need to keep burning until they've actually completely reversed course
还需要一直点火到改变了速度方向
heading backwards from the original velocity and make their ballistic trajectory end up at the landing site
并且使其弹道最终落在着陆点
or just short of the landing site for safety reasons.
或为了安全起见 只在着陆点附近
After the engines shut down,
在发动机关闭后
the boosters will be coasting back to the launch site,
助推器将滑行返回发射场
seeing as they're well above a hundred kilometers at this time,
考虑到箭体此时远在距离地面百公里以上
they have no air resistance to slow them down.
它们没有空气阻力来减缓它们的速度
So during this period, the cold gas thrusters on the Falcon 9
所以在这期间 猎鹰9号的冷气推进器
home in and precisely target the landing site using little tiny puffs of nitrogen.
利用推力微小的氮气将箭体精确对准着陆场
Starship will use its hot gas thrusters for any of these maneuvers.
Starship将使用它的热气推进器进行这些操作
But the idea is basically the same.
但想法基本上是一样的
Small, tiny impulses can help precisely point and guide the booster back home.
小小的推力可以帮助精确地指向并引导助推器回家
During this phase, they will deploy the grid fins,
在这个阶段 他们将部署栅格翼
although in the vacuum of space, they obviously don't provide any control yet.
虽然在真空中 显然还不能提供任何控制
So the boosters will follow their ballistic trajectory
那么助推器会按照它们的弹道轨迹运行
and eventually they'll both begin to experience more and of the earth atmospheric pressure.
最终 它们都会开始经历更多的地球大气压力
The air in front of the booster will heat up due to being compressed by the leading surface,
助推器前面的空气会被迎风面压缩加热
due to the laws of thermodynamics.
这是由于热力学定律
As air is compressed, it's heated up.
当空气被压缩时 就会被加热
The air in the bow shock compresses so much.
弓形激波中的空气被压缩得很厉害
It actually turns into a plasma.
实际上变成了一种等离子体
This plasma can be about half as hot as the surface of the sun.
这种等离子体的温度可以达到太阳表面的一半
Here's where the Falcon 9 does something that's Super Heavy is hoping to avoid.
猎鹰9号在这里做了一些超重助推器希望避免的事情
The Falcon 9 will again, light up three of its 9 Merlin engines
猎鹰9号将再次点燃9台灰背隼发动机中的3台
to slow itself down just as it begins to really experience those extreme atmospheric temperatures.
在它开始真正经历那些极端的大气温度时 就会减慢自己的速度
This not only slows the booster down,
这不仅会使助推器减速
but it also basically creates a force field in front of the booster,
但也基本上在助推器前形成了一个力场
providing a boundary of exhaust gas, which is a lot cooler than the plasma.
提供一个比等离子体冷却得多的废气形成的边界
Without this step, the Falcon 9 booster would likely not survive the re-entry process.
如果没有这一步 猎鹰9号一级很可能无法扛过再入过程
After all SpaceX tried to recover the Falcon 1 and Falcon 9 boosters using parachutes for the first few flights,
毕竟在最初的几次飞行中 SpaceX曾试图用降落伞来回收猎鹰1号和猎鹰9号一级
which kept failing.
但一直失败
By the time the booster was supposed to deploy the parachute,
到了助推器应该展开降落伞的时候
it was too late because it's hard to deploy parachutes when you're in a million flaming pieces.
为时已晚 因为当你烧成碎片的时候 很难部署降落伞
But again, as we mentioned before,
但是 同样 正如我们之前所提到的
this is something that stainless steel should allow the Super Heavy booster to forgo,
这一点 得益于不锈钢材质 超重助推器应该可以放弃这个点火过程
which will save fuel and thereby increase overall performance.
这将节省燃料 从而提高整体性能
Because of its much higher melting point,
由于其熔点更高
Super Heavy is hoping to just grit its teeth through this process and survive this brutal regimen.
超重助推器有希望在这个过程中咬紧牙关 熬过这个残酷的疗程
And I think they can do it.
我认为他们可以做到这一点
I mean, after all Rocket Lab's Electron rocket has survived this portion of flight
我是说 毕竟火箭实验室的Electron火箭 已经在这段飞行中幸存下来了
that Peter Beck is calling the wall
也就是Peter Beck所说的墙
and that rocket is made from carbon composite.
而那枚火箭是由碳纤维复合材料制成的
So it's definitely possible.
所以这绝对有可能
Although comparing these two vehicles might not be too fair.
虽然比较这两种航天器可能不太公平
From this point on the grid fins have more and more control.
从这开始 栅格翼的控制力越来越强
Grid fins are basically just hundreds of small fins stacked side by side.
栅格翼基本上就是几百个小翼面并排堆叠在一起
This allows them to be tucked out of the airstream on ascent,
这样就可以在上升段 把它们折叠起来 而不影响气流
and then they're deployed into an atmospheric cheese grater when coming back down.
然后在回来的时候 被部署成一个大气的奶酪粉碎机
People often think the grid fins are just an air break
人们常常认为栅格翼只是一个空气刹车
or something to help keep the center of pressure behind the center of mass.
或其他有助于保持压力中心在质量中心后面(的空气动力组件)
But really they steer just like an all moving control surface,
但其实它们的转向就像一个全动的控制面
like the stabilators on the tail of the F-16.
就像F-16的全动平尾一样
The entire thing rotates around a central point to induce control.
整个翼面围绕一个中心点旋转 以进行控制
For grid fins, they can move opposite pairs in unison to provide pitch or yaw
对于栅格翼 它们可以一致地移动对侧的翼面 以提供俯仰或偏航
and they can all move opposite their pair for roll.
而且交错地移动对侧翼面就可以滚转
The grid fins now steer really hard and point the boosters back towards the landing site.
栅格翼现在真的很努力地转向并将助推器指向着陆场
They can even pitch in a way that creates lift along the booster's fuselage
它们甚至能俯仰到一种沿助推器箭体产生升力的姿态
and help it translate even further over.
从而进一步大幅调整轨迹
I should probably point out that all of this is guided autonomously
我也许应该指出 所有这些都是自主引导的
based on GPS and altitude and all of the other measurements
这基于GPS 海拔高度以及其他所有的测量数据
that the rocket has to try and point itself at a precise target.
火箭必须尝试并指向一个精确的目标
So it's not like someone's sitting there steering this thing.
那么这并不像有人坐在那里操纵这个东西
By utilizing as much of the booster as possible to basically glide
通过尽可能地让助推器来进行滑翔飞行
it also allows the air to slow it down as much as possible,
这还可以让空气尽可能地减缓火箭的速度
which requires less fuel for the final landing burn.
这样 最后的着陆点火可以节省燃料
Now, unlike ascent, where the air is fighting against the rocket,
那么 与上升段空气是在对抗火箭的运动的作用不同
here, the atmosphere is helping to remove energy.
在这里 大气层有助于减少能量
So eventually the booster will line itself up directly overhead of the landing site.
所以最终助推器会对准着陆场正上方
At the last possible moment they light up their engines.
在最后可能着陆的时刻 他们会点燃发动机
And in the case of the Falcon 9, this has to be extremely precisely timed.
对于猎鹰9号来说 时间必须非常精确
The nearly empty Falcon 9 booster,
对于几乎是空的猎鹰9号一级
even when only one of its 9 Merlin engines is running at its minimum throttle setting,
即使它的9个灰背隼发动机中只有一台以最小节流状态点火
still has too much thrust to just hover.
仍然有太大的推力 而不能进行悬停
So they have to perform,
所以他们必须要执行
what's been called a hover slam or a less astronaut friendly term, a suicide burn.
被称为悬停式撞击 或者一个对宇航员不太友好的术语 自杀式点火
This is where you light up your engines as late as possible.
也就是发动机点火要尽可能地晚
So late, you don't have a second chance.
但太晚了 你就没有第二次机会了
And because of the high thrust to weight ratio,
而且由于推重比很高
不一定零速度，但要在很小的速度范围内
they have to reach zero velocity right at zero altitude.
他们必须要在零高度刚好达到零速度
Otherwise the booster will end up going right back up.
否则助推器就会直接上升回去
Starship, Super Heavy booster on the other hand will land using only its inner engines.
另一方面 Starship和超重助推器将只使用其中间的发动机着陆
These are the only engines that can gimbal and eventually they'll be the only ones that can deep throttle,
也就是唯一可以矢量摆动的发动机 最终也是唯一可以深度节流的发动机
which is necessary for soft propulsive landings.
这是反推式软着陆所必需的
The outer ring of engines will someday be those booster variants of Raptor that are higher thrust,
总有一天 外圈的发动机会使用那些推力更大的 专用于助推器的伶盗龙的变种
but they can't deep throttle and they're fixed in place with no ability to gimbal.
但不能深度节流 而且是固定的 不能矢量摆动
Super Heavy could probably technically hover,
超重助推器技术上可能可以悬停
but you really don't want to do that.
但你真的不想这样做
After all hovering is just 100% a waste of fuel.
毕竟悬停只是完全在浪费燃料
All the fuel spend to hover is literally getting you nowhere.
所有花在悬停上的燃料都没有产生位移
It's best to do the burn as late as you can.
最好就是尽晚点火
And with as much acceleration as you can.
同时加速度尽可能地大
The shorter, the burn, the more efficient,
越短 点火效率更高
but the good news is Super Heavy has the option to do a slower, less efficient burn,
但好消息是超重助推器可以选择进行更慢 更低效的点火过程
if they, for some reason want it to.
如果他们出于某种原因希望这样做
From here, the Falcon 9 lowers its landing legs,
从这里开始 猎鹰9号放下了它的着陆腿
应该是氦气气压驱动的
www.quora.com/What-is-the-folding-mechanism-of-the-SpaceX-Falcon-9-landing-legs
which are hydraulically pushed out and then locked into place.
用液压将其推出 然后锁定到位
Super Heavy will probably not have to extend its landing legs because they'll likely be fixed.
超重助推器可能不需要展开它的着陆腿 因为它们很可能是被固定住的
At least that's what we know right now.
至少现在我们知道的是这样
Once the rockets land, they of course shut down the engines
一旦火箭着陆 它们当然会关闭发动机
and begin to lower the tank pressures to something safe enough for humans to approach.
并开始将储罐压力降低到足以让人类接近的安全状态
For the Falcon 9 once it's clear to proceed,
对于猎鹰9号来说 一旦明确可以继续(回收流程)
a crew will actually go out there and pick it up by two cranes
就会有一组人员去那里用两台吊车把它吊起来
and lay it flat on its side on a trailer.
然后把它平放在拖车上
From here, they'll take it back to a hangar
他们会把火箭从这里运到机库
where they'll do a bit of checkouts and refurbishment.
在那里他们会做一些检查和翻新
The Merlin engines often need a good check over and potential clean outs because of that buildup of soot.
由于烟尘的堆积 灰背隼发动机经常需要好好检查 并可能需要清理
The quickest turnaround to date is about 50 days before it can be reflown,
到目前为止 最快的周转时间是50天左右 然后才能重新飞行
although that time is decreasing quickly.
虽然这个时间正在迅速减少
But this will all hopefully be unnecessary someday for Super Heavy,
但有朝一日 超重助推器都有希望摆脱这一切
since the plan will eventually be to just pick it back up and put it right back on the launchpad
因为最终的计划会是把它捡回来 再放回到发射台上
and thanks to reusable nature of the Raptor engine and Methalox,
由于伶盗龙发动机和液氧甲烷的可重复使用性
this might become a reality someday,
这也许有一天这会成为现实
or maybe it'll be similar to kicking the tires like a jetliner before each flight
也许就像喷气式飞机每次飞行前的踢轮胎一样
doing a simple checkout before reflying, hopefully.
做一个简单的检查 然后复飞 希望如此
有什么不同？
二级火箭重复使用
So now let's look at the upper stages of the Falcon 9 and Starship.
那么现在我们来看看猎鹰9号和Starship的上面级
SpaceX is already pursuing reuse beyond the first stage
SpaceX已经在追求一级火箭以外的重复使用
by catching and reusing the nose cone or fairings on the Falcon 9.
比如抓住并重复使用猎鹰9号的鼻锥或整流罩
SpaceX has even reused the same fairing three times already.
SpaceX甚至已经使用同一个整流罩三次了
And this is great considering that they cost several millions of dollars.
而考虑到它们的成本是几百万美元 这就很好了
It just makes sense.
这就是合情合理的
They're Wile E. Coyote scheme to catch them has been paying off.
他们这威利狼式的计划已经得到了回报
And even when they miss a catch,
即使当他们错过了一次整流罩捕获的时候
simply fishing them out of the water has proven worthwhile too.
事实证明 仅仅从水中捞出它们也是值得的
But despite all of these reuse efforts,
但尽管有这些重复使用的努力
the second stage itself is always discarded.
但二级本身总是被丢弃的
After the Falcon 9 deploys his payload, it either does a deorbit burn
在猎鹰9号部署有效载荷后 它要么进行离轨点火
and discards the upper stage in a pre-planned exclusion zone on earth,
并在地球上预先计划好的禁区内丢弃上面级
or it kicks itself out into what's called a graveyard orbit.
否则就会点火进入所谓的坟场轨道
But here's where SpaceX is going absolute next level with Starship.
但在这儿 SpaceX的Starship绝对会更上一层楼
I know I've been saying that a lot, but this is the hard part.
我知道我已经说了很多 但这是最难的部分
Despite the upper stage being a smaller portion of the rocket,
尽管上面级是火箭的一小部分
it's substantially harder,
实质上更难
maybe even an order of magnitude harder to recover something going at orbital velocity
甚至可能超出一个数量级的难度 才能回收这种达到轨道速度的物体
compared to recovering a suborbital stage.
与回收亚轨道的分级(一级)相比
This is the biggest paradigm shift that Starship is hoping to achieve.
这是Starship希望实现的最大模式转变
The hardest and most cumbersome problem is speed.
最难 最麻烦的问题是速度
Minimum orbital velocity is around 28,000 kilometers an hour.
最低轨道速度是28000千米/小时左右
Yes, literally about 10 times faster than a bullet.
是的 真是比子弹快10倍左右
This means things that are up in orbit are traveling eight kilometers or five miles each and every second.
这意味着入轨的物体 都在以8公里/秒或5英里/秒的速度运行
So the booster imparts a decent amount of the sideways velocity,
那么助推器带来了相当大的侧向速度
but a booster's maximum velocity is only about 1/3 to 1/4 of the speed that the second stage reaches.
但助推器的最大速度只有二级速度的三分之一到四分之一
Now you might be thinking, Oh, well, three or four times faster.
那么你可能会想 哦 好吧 快了三四倍
Why is that any harder to return?
那为什么返回会更难呢？
Especially if it's smaller.
尤其是当它的体积更小的时候
A vehicle that's going 28,000 kilometers an hour
一个时速28000公里的飞行器
needs to slow back down to pretty much zero kilometers an hour to not smash into the ground.
需要减速到差不多零公里的时速才不至于撞到地面
So that means all of that energy needs to be removed from the vehicle somehow.
所以这意味着所有的能量都需要以某种方式从飞行器上消除
And again, just like when the atmosphere slowed the booster down,
就像大气层让助推器减速一样
we can now use the atmosphere to slow the upper stage down too.
我们现在也可以利用大气层来减缓上面级的速度
The problem is the temperature of the compressive heating in the bow shock of a vehicle
问题是航天器的弓形激波中的压缩加热的温度
doesn't increase linearly with speed.
不会随着速度的增加而线性增加
No, it's not like you.
不 它不像你想的那样
If you go twice as fast, the temperature gets twice as high.
如果速度快一倍 温度就会高一倍
That'd be child's play.
那可是过家家
It's not even the heating goes up by velocity squared.
甚至都不是按速度的平方上升的
So go twice as fast and the heating is four times as much.
也就是 速度快一倍 温度就高四倍
No, no, no.
不不不
Re-entry heating goes up by the cube of velocity.
再入大气层的热量是速度的立方
So go twice as fast, create eight times as much heat.
所以 速度快一倍 产生的热量是八倍
Ouch.
嘿呀
So since the upper stage is traveling at say four times faster than the first stage as it reenters,
所以 由于上面级再入的速度比一级快四倍
it can experience up to 64 times as much heat.
它会经历高达64倍的热量
That's why recovering the upper stage is so stinking hard.
这就是为什么回收上面级是如此的困难
Now you might be tempted to think, well,
那么你可能会想 好吧
b23.tv/av498215348
why don't you just slow down before you enter?
你为什么不在进入之前减速呢？
And that way you could get back down to those same velocities and temperatures as the booster.
这样你就能回到和助推器一样的速度和温度
Well, in order to slow back down using your rocket engines in the frictionless environment of space,
好吧 为了在无摩擦的太空环境中使用火箭发动机减速
it would require exactly as much energy as it did to get up to that speed in the first place.
首先 它所需要的能量和最初达到这个速度所需要的能量是一样的
So that means you'd basically have to have as big of a rocket on orbit,
所以这意味着你基本上必须在轨道上有同样大的火箭
capable of slowing you down as the one that you took off with,
这样才能够让你慢下来
which would of course mean that the rocket that would launch that rocket
这当然意味着 发射这枚火箭的火箭
would need to be like 10 times bigger too.
也需要大10倍左右
So the solution that SpaceX came up with for this problem was
所以SpaceX针对这个问题提出的解决方案就是
to use as much of Starship as possible to slow down in the atmosphere.
尽可能多地利用Starship在大气层中减速
So they will enter the atmosphere belly first,
那么他们会用机腹朝前的姿态再入大气层
exposing as much cross section of the vehicle into the windstream as possible.
让航天器尽可能多的截面暴露在气流中
This is why SpaceX's, Starship will reenter more like a skydiver
这也是为什么SpaceX的Starship会更像跳伞运动员一样再入
and it won't go in engines first, like the Falcon 9 or at a 40 degree angle, like the Space Shuttle.
而它不会像猎鹰9号那样发动机朝前 也不会像航天飞机那样用40度角
It'll basically be slamming on the brakes as much as possible.
基本上就是尽可能地猛踩刹车
Although they can pitch and kind of create some lift to manage peak temperatures,
虽然他们可以俯仰 也算是创造一些升力来控制峰值温度
in general, it has to use as much surface area
一般来说 它必须尽可能地使用更多的表面积
to really just distribute that heat as much as possible and slow down as much as they can.
让热量分散得更开 并让航天器减速得更多
Now, in order to do this,
那么 为了做到这一点
it needs to be able to control and maintain stability.
它需要能够控制并保持稳定性
That's exactly what those Eloneron we talked about earlier are for.
这正是我们之前说的那些马翼龙的作用
They change their drag to control pitch yaw and roll.
这些翼面可以改变阻力来控制俯仰 偏航和滚转
Reentering the atmosphere allows the vehicle
再入大气层可以让航天器
to exchange all of that insane amount of kinetic energy it has for heat.
将所有这些疯狂的动能转换为热能
Think of the atmosphere as a giant brake pad, which does the same thing,
把大气层想象成一个巨大的刹车片 也是一样的
A brake pad exchanges kinetic energy through heat from friction.
刹车片通过摩擦把动能转换为热能
Only in this case, it's not air friction that causes the heat,
只是在这种情况下 并不是空气摩擦引起的热量
like we mentioned before,
就像我们之前提到的
it's compression of the air and the bow shock that heats up the vehicle
是空气的压缩以及弓形激波加热了航天器
and again, this is why they went with stainless steel.
这也是他们要用不锈钢的原因
So it can survive re-entry intact.
所以它能完好无损地再入大气层
Now SpaceX has done something brilliant here.
那么 在这方面 SpaceX已经做了一些很不错的东西
Something that the Space Shuttle did not have.
也就是航天飞机所没有的东西
They made uniform heat shield tiles.
他们制造了统一的隔热瓦
Since, you know, the whole Starship is basically just a giant cylinder
因为整个Starship基本上就是一个巨大的圆柱体
besides the nose where it tapers and those hinges and stuff.
除了锥形的鼻子和那些铰链之类的东西的表面形状比较怪
Now this will make for way easier checkouts, easy production and easy manufacturing.
那么 通用的隔热瓦会让检查 生产和制造的难度大为下降
Now we don't know a ton of specifics about the heat shield,
关于隔热板 现在我们还不知道很多细节
Toughened Uni-Piece Fibrous Reinforced Oxidation-Resistant Composite
(钢化单片纤维增强型耐氧化复合材料)
other than they're likely to be an in-house variant of a material called TUFROC,
除了它们很可能是一种叫做TUFROC材料的内部修改版之外
which touts higher usability by being able to handle high peak temperatures before ablating.
这种材料能在烧蚀前承受高峰值的温度来达到更高的可用性
Now there might be some hotspots that'll ablate a little bit each launch
那么每次发射都会消融一些较热的区域
but because they're uniform,
但因为它们是统一的
they should be easy to swap out and replace when they get low.
可以在隔热瓦变薄的时候 容易地进行替换
And again, it's kind of just like a brake pad.
再说一遍 这是有点像刹车片
Eventually these tiles will be mechanically mounted
最终 这些隔热瓦将被机械地安装
and likely done so by an automated robot for quick and easy manufacturing and replacement,
而且很可能是由自动化的机器人来完成的 以实现快速 便捷的制造和替换
and these heat shields might be one of the only things that really ever wears down
而这些隔热板可能是为数不多的真正会磨损的东西
and will require maintenance on the entire rocket, at least in a perfect world.
同时需要在整枚火箭上进行维护 当然是理想情况下
Okay. Okay.
好吧 好吧
So Starship eventually gets slowed down from going 10 times faster than a bullet
那么Starship最终会从比子弹快10倍的速度减慢下来
to a relatively slow terminal velocity of maybe a couple hundred kilometers an hour
其终端速度相对较慢 也许每小时几百公里
falling straight down now, but still belly first.
现在直挺挺地下降 但还是机腹朝前的姿态
And here's the thing that's going to be truly absolutely insane to see.
而这里 将是真正绝对疯狂的看点
Starship will still need to land using its sea level Raptor engines.
Starship仍需要使用它的海平面伶盗龙发动机来着陆
And as you might recall, those engines are on the bottom of the rocket,
而你可能还记得 这些发动机在火箭的底部
which at this exact moment are facing sideways, completely horizontally.
此时此刻 它们正朝向侧面 完全水平
Hmm. The solution to this,
嗯 为了解决这个问题
a wild daring and potentially hard to nail down belly flop to tail down maneuver.
会进行一个野蛮大胆且有可能难以确定的 机腹向下到尾部向下的机动动作
This has been over, it will make the Falcon 9's landing look like a walk in the park.
如果完成了这个机动 就会让猎鹰9号的着陆看上去十分简单
It's a maneuver that would probably make the best stunt pilots in the world, poop their pants.
这是一个可能会让世界上最好的特技飞行员 屎拉裤子上的动作
The first attempts at this will look a little bit different than the eventual system,
第一次的尝试会和最终的系统看起来有些不同
because the cold gas thrusters on early prototypes aren't very powerful
因为早期原型机上的冷气推进器并不是很强大
and can't aid too much in that flip maneuver.
并不能过多地辅助该翻转动作
But for the initial prototype, the rear Elonerons will tuck in to aid in the rotation.
但对于最初的原型机来说 后部的马翼龙将会收拢 以辅助旋转
And the three Raptors will light up while going horizontally.
而三台伶盗龙发动机会在水平方向点火
However, they'll be at maximum tilt,
不过 它们会处于最大的摆动状态
pitching the rockets nose up as quickly as they can.
尽快把火箭的箭头翘起来
Of course, in doing so, it's going to inject a heck of a lot of horizontal velocity.
当然 在这样做的时候 会注入大量的水平速度
So in order to negate that and land on their target,
所以 为了消除这种情况 并在目标上着陆
it's going to need to, over-correct, swinging back over to the other side,
它要需要 过度修正 也就是回旋到另一边
canceling out the horizontal before straightening out and touching down softly.
消除水平速度 然后才直起身子 轻轻地着陆
And they're about to try this for the first time.
而他们即将第一次尝试这个动作
And I'm sitting here wondering what's going to make me just lose my mind more.
而我坐在这里 想知道什么会让我更加石乐智
If they stick that landing, I think I'll lose my mind,
如果他们坚持那样(成功)着陆 我想我会石乐智
but also if they just belly flop and blow up.
但一样的 如果他们只是进行机腹向下俯冲的机动 然后爆炸 我也会石乐智
Well, regardless what the outcome, it'll be spectacular.
嗯 不管结果如何 都会很壮观
Eventually on more production ready and advanced versions,
最终在更高级且更接近量产的版本上
when they get to those hot gas thrusters,
也就是他们有了那些热气推进器的时候
this maneuver should be able to be done completely by the thrusters and the Elonerons,
这个动作应该完全可以由推进器和马翼龙来完成
then it'd just be a simple hover slam landing, just like a Falcon 9.
那就只是一个简单的悬停式撞击 就像猎鹰9号一样
This maneuver is extremely important
这个动作非常重要
because when you're trying to land a vehicle this size on Mars, there's no runway.
因为当你想在火星上着陆一个这么大的航天器时 是没有跑道的
There's no way you can glide and land on wheels.
你不可能(在火星上)滑翔并用轮子降落
You have to nail this maneuver.
你必须得搞定这个动作
This has to be easy peasy here on earth and done over and over again
这必须得在地球上一遍又一遍地 轻而易举地完成
before we put humans on it and then send them off to Mars.
之后再尝试载人 然后再使用Starship把人类送上火星
Now I should probably point out here.
现在我应该指出的是
Another thing that we get asked about quite a bit, and that's the landing legs on Starship.
也是经常被问到的事情 那就是Starship的着陆腿
For now, the landing legs are pretty small and tucked inside the skirt of Starship prototypes,
目前 着陆腿非常小 而且藏在Starship原型机的裙板内
but they'll eventually evolve and be upgraded quite a bit.
但它们终究会进行不小的升级
After all, when it comes to landing on the moon or Mars,
毕竟 在着陆月球或者火星的时候
you may encounter some uneven ground or boulders.
你可能会遇到一些不平整的地面或大石头
So these legs will someday be self leveling,
那么终有一天 这些脚能够自动调平
which although we don't have too many details about right now
虽然我们现在还不知道很多细节
is probably one of the easiest technologies on Starship.
而这可能是Starship上最简单的技术之一
I mean, come on.
我是说 拜托
If a camper can do it, it can't be that hard.
如果一个露营车都能做到 那就不难
But there's one really big technology that will debut on Starship
但有一项非常重要的技术将在Starship上首次亮相
that will be required to get humans to Mars.
需要这个技术才能将人类送上火星
And that's on orbit refueling.
那就是推进剂在轨补加
Remember how we talked about
还记得我们前面说到的
how Starship didn't really necessarily have a huge payload capacity to geostationary transfer orbit
那就是Starship怎么会真的不需要很大的GTO运载能力
because it has to lug around all of its dry mass.
因为它要带着所有的干质量到处跑
Well, Starship can make up for that by refueling in orbit.
好吧 Starship可以通过在轨补加来弥补这一点
If this vehicle really is rapidly reusable
如果这个航天器真的可以快速重复使用
and the Super Heavy booster can just land
而超重助推器可以直接着陆
and grab a Starship tanker and launch again on the next orbit,
并与一艘Starship储罐版组合起来 在下一次(交会)的轨道上再次发射
this could be the most important technology.
那么这就可能是其所需的最重要的技术
By refueling Starship on orbit,
通过在轨道上为Starship加油
it would have an astonishing amount of Delta-v and could easily get to the moon or Mars with fuel to spare.
它将拥有惊人的dv 可以带着燃料轻松地到达月球或火星
But something like this has never really been demonstrated,
但这样的事情从来没被真正地验证过
not at this scale and not with cryogenic propellants.
要么没有这么大规模 要么不是低温推进剂
But luckily SpaceX has even gotten NASA invested in this effort.
但幸运的是 在这方面 SpaceX甚至已经得到了NASA的投资
For now it's a $53 million contract
目前 这是一份5300万美元的合同
to study transferring cryogenic oxygen between the header tanks and the main tanks.
以研究在主储罐和副储罐之间传输低温液氧
But eventually they'll hopefully be interested in seeing Starship to Starship refueling too.
但最终他们也希望能看到Starship对Starship的补加
But like I said, at the top of this episode,
但就像我在这集的开头所说的
there are some other variants that we might see someday,
我们有一天可能会看到一些其他的Starship衍生版
like versions that are just completely stripped down,
像是完全拆光部件的版本
maybe just a single or a few vacuum optimized Raptors
也许只装有一台或几台真空优化的伶盗龙发动机
capable of taking huge payloads out to the outer Solar System.
这就能把巨大的有效载荷带到外太阳系去
That would make sense because you're not going to be retrieving that stage.
这就说得通了 因为你不打算回收那个分级
And don't forget about the lunar Lander version of Starship that we've talked about a little bit,
不要忘了我们之前说过的月球着陆器版本的Starship
that too is its own stripped down version that will never have to reenter.
那也是一种不需要再入地球大气而去除部件的版本
So they are kind of doing that a little bit,
所以他们算是(为一次性使用)做了一定的工作
but even that vehicle will still need to be refueled on orbit.
但即使是这样的航天器也需要在轨补加
So all said and done Starship takes reuse up the next level
所以说 Starship将重复使用提升到了一个新的高度
potentially to Elon's ultimate goal of a rapidly reusable orbital rocket.
有可能达到马一龙的最终目标 也就是快速重复使用的轨道级火箭
As he says, often, if you designed an expendable jetliner,
正如他所说 往往 如果你设计了一架一次性的喷气式客机
you'd get left out of the room.
你就已经被淘汰了
So Starship could truly usher in a new era of Spaceflight.
因此 Starship可能真的开创一个新的航天时代
总结
Starship is simply a massively ambitious proposition,
Starship是一个非常艰巨的计划
but there's few physical barriers, which would make it impossible
但几乎没有物理学上的障碍 使其无法完成
other than it's never been done.
只是这之前没人做过而已
And like anything that's never been done before, the unknowns are unknown.
就像任何从未做过的事情一样 存在许多未知
I fully expect Starship to have some stumbling blocks along the way
我完全相信Starship会在前进的道路上会遇到一些障碍
and learn some valuable lessons too.
并吸取一些宝贵的经验教训
They'll likely be many more explosions along the path to orbit.
他们很可能会在入轨前发生更多的爆炸
And even once operational, I mean, remember the Falcon 9,
而且即使一旦投入使用 我是指 还记得猎鹰9号吗
hasn't always been smooth sailing either.
也不是一直一帆风顺的
Nothing is when you're pushing the boundaries either,
当你在挑战极限的时候 总会遇到波折
but now the Falcon 9 is one of the most reliable and most flown rockets.
但现在猎鹰9号是最可靠 飞行次数最多的火箭之一
What used to be an experimental landing is now expected and almost mundane.
过去的实验性着陆 现在已经是意料之中的 几乎是司空见惯了
After all Elon has said in the past that he hopes these landings become so routine that they're boring.
毕竟马一龙过去曾说过 他希望这些着陆变得非常常规 以至于无聊
And although I'm personally not quite to that point yet, it is getting close.
虽然我个人还没到那个地步 但已经很接近了
So to summarize Starship takes everything SpaceX learned from the Falcon 9
所以总结一下 Starship把SpaceX从猎鹰9号身上学到的一切
and upgrades it into a brand new, Super Heavy lift rocket that's rapidly and fully reusable.
并将其升级为全新的超级重型运载火箭 而且可快速 完全地重复使用
It's going to be huge, the biggest and most powerful rocket ever made.
这将是巨大的 有史以来最大和最强大的火箭
They're utilizing methane that burns clean and is efficient.
他们使用的是能清洁 高效地燃烧的甲烷
They developed the Raptor engine, which is a compact and efficient workhorse.
他们开发了紧凑而高效的主发动机 伶盗龙发动机
They're scaling the vehicle up to a huge degree
他们正在将火箭的规模扩大到一个新的台阶
so they can pursue full reuse without sacrificing performance
所以他们可以在不牺牲性能的情况下追求完全的重复使用
and in fact, increasing performance.
而且实际上也是在提高性能
And perhaps most importantly, they're trying out new landing techniques
而也许最重要的是 他们正在尝试新的着陆技术
that despite being absolutely bonkers by design
尽管是绝对疯狂的设计
should potentially solve the problem surviving re-entry and land propulsively on a dime.
但这应该可以解决再入大气层后的生存问题 并能短距离反推式着陆
We'll see lots of Starships.
我们会看到很多Starship
Starship Tankers, Starship People Carriers, Starship Lunar version, Starship Cargo versions,
Starship储罐版 Starship载人版 Starship登月版 Starship货运版
et cetera, et cetera.
诸如此类x2
And all of this is in pursuit of getting human beings to Mars,
而所有这些都是为了把人类送上火星
which when you solve that,
当你解决这个问题时
just so happens to make rockets a whole lot more capable
恰好让火箭的性能提高了很多
and a whole lot cheaper here on earth too.
而且在地球上也便宜了很多
Starship will truly usher in a new era and that is not hyperbole.
Starship将真正开创一个新的时代 这并不是夸大其词
So what do you think,
那你觉得呢
do you think Starship will live up to its ambitions?
Do you think SpaceX will actually recover and reuse the entire rocket?
Or do you think plans will change?
Do you think this vehicle will actually take humans to Mars or is it all just a giant pipe dream?
Let me know your thoughts or if you have any other questions in the comments below,
but the good news is if you have questions and you want to just dive into this more,
I already have a ton of videos for you that go even deeper into a bunch of these topics.
In fact, I put together a whole Starship playlist.
Now that has videos like my interview with Elon about Starship,
SLS versus Starship, the Raptor engine,
why Starhip won't have an abort system?
Why are they using stainless steel instead of carbon fiber?
Why Starship will belly flop and a few others links to that playlist
and each individual video is in the description below. Now,
be sure you're subscribed and stick around because I'll be interviewing Elon Musk again here very soon.
And I'm going to be sure and ask about all the upcoming changes in case we missed anything
and also kind of follow up on some of those things that I was a little bit vague about in this video,
because we just don't have those answers yet.
So fingers crossed we don't get any huge surprises and it doesn't immediately just date this video,
please. And also in the description,
you're going to see links for Caspar Stanley's awesome work,
including his awesome rocket Explorer app.
You guys have to check this out, it's available on steam or coming really soon.
It's kind of in the middle as I'm shooting this,
but you can check it out is an awesome app that shows you different rockets and all these things.
His renders are amazing and you definitely have to be following him on Twitter
because he has some of the coolest content.
Another quick shout out to Erc space on Twitter at E R C X space
who provided a few of those awesome videos too.
And I also thanks to Corey at sea bass 3d productions,
and that's at C underscore bass 3d on Twitter.
Definitely follow his work too.
I know there's sometimes huge gaps between my videos
because I want the quality to be the best they possibly can be.
And I can only do that because of the support of my Patreon supporters.
If you want to help make what I do possible head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut,
there you'll gain access to exclusive live streams.
You'll gain early access to scripts where you can give your input
or ask questions about videos before they come out and help make these videos better.
But you can also gain access to our exclusive subreddit and our exclusive discord channel,
which is just an awesome place to hang out.
We have just the that's community full of really fun people that are,
we're all done learning together constantly. I hang out there all the time.
So if you want to join our awesome community,
head over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut, thank you.
And while you're online,
you definitely need to check out our web store everydayastronaut.
com/shop where you'll find shirts like this future Martian society shirts,
which has a ton of nerdy details. Like I talked about.
This shirt is just jam packed.
First off the side has the gravity and the atmospheric composition of Mars,
which I figured to be, you know, since we're talking about Starship,
which is going to Mars, definitely a fitting shirt,
but there's way more to it than that,
because notice it says Arcadia Planacia in the little logo,
and then it has some coordinates.
Those are the exact landing coordinates of the proposed candidate A landing site for Starship.
So this way you can just show off how nerdy you are because you're wearing a
shirt that might have the first place. Humans are going to walk on Mars,
the exact coordinates already printed out there for you,
but don't forget to check out all of our other awesome stuff like the full flow
stage combustion cycle shirt and the brand new, super awesome hoodie.
We also have things like key chains and just tons of stuff.
We're constantly making upgrades to the shop.
So head on over to everydayastronaut.com/shop.
Thanks everybody. That's going to do it for me.
谢谢大家观看 本期节目到这里就结束了
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人